University of Connecticut, Labor Education Center Records 1981.0005
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
University of Connecticut, Labor Education Center Records
undated, 1948-1970
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1981.0005
12.75 Linear Feet
First established as a program within the Labor Management Institute in 1946, the Labor Education evolved into a separate center in 1961. Its purpose is to fulfill the educational, consultation, and research needs of the state's unions.
History
First established as a program within the Labor Management Institute in 1946, Labor Education evolved into a separate center in 1961. Its purpose is to fulfill the educational, consultation and research needs of the state's unions, employee organization and their members in the field of labor education. The Center also seeks to provide a greater understanding of the labor movement on the part of government officials, business leaders, the University community and the general public.
As the Labor Education Center's first director, John Glynn established many of the goals and priorities that continue to guide the center today. Dr. Glynn began working as an instructor for LMI when it was founded in 1946. Throughout his long career, Dr. Glynn strongly influenced the Center's policy development. Upon John Glynn's death in 1979, George E. O'Connell became director of the Center. Mark Sullivan has also served as director.
Scope and Content
The Labor Education Center records are arranged in twelve series, and contain records pertaining to Labor Education Center staff, directors, and also to unions, organizations, the WACAP, LEC-sponsored programs, courses, conferences, seminars, workshops, and numerous other labor-related publications, history, records, reports, and similar materials as they relate to labor education and the Labor Education Center.
Arrangement
Series I: Personnel Files (1954-1966) [RESTRICTED] contains the records of the Labor Education Center staff. Folders include employee evaluations, attendance records, employee vitae, salary information, correspondence and memoranda, and minutes of staff meetings. One folder contains job applications for LEC positions. The series is arranged alphabetically by employee name. Personnel files in this series are restricted. For information about access, contact the University Archivist.
Series II: John Glynn Files(1949-1968) contains the records kept by Dr. Glynn during his years with LMI and in his capacity as director of the LEC. The files are arranged alphabetically in five subseries: General, Labor Education Center; Courses and Workshops; Labor Management Institute; Publications; and University of Philippines. The bulk of the series is comprised of subject files. Other types of material included are correspondence, printed material, contracts and agreements, minutes, notes, and memoranda.
Series III: Unions and Organizations(undated) contains general information, promotional leaflets, newsletters and other printed material created by or regarding various state unions and organizations. The series is arranged alphabetically by organization.
Series IV: Windham Area Community Action Program [WACAP](undated, 1965-1970) contains the records of a local agency that designed and implemented programs aimed at aiding the poor and disadvantaged. Typical of these programs were Headstart and Legal Aid Society. John Glynn served as a member of WACAP's board of directors and collected the bulk of these files. The series is primarily composed of administrative and subject files regarding WACAP sponsored programs. Correspondence and memoranda, minutes of board meetings, annual reports, publications and newsclippings, and policy statements are also included.
Series V: Extension Programs (undated, 1948-1968) is composed of records documenting LEC-sponsored courses and conferences held throughout the state. The series is arranged alphabetically by the town where programs were held. Program content is not always identified on the folder listing.
Series VI: LEC-sponsored Conferences(undated, 1947-1969) documents conferences held for various state organizations and unions or concerning a specific labor-related topic. The series is arranged alphabetically by conference name and includes conference packet material, handouts and attachments, agendas, correspondence, and memoranda.
Series VII, Labor Training Programs (undated, 1949-1969) contains information regarding LEC-sponsored courses offered to specific labor organizations. The series is arranged alphabetically by the town in which the programs were held. The organization receiving training is also identified.
Series VIII: Corporate-sponsored Seminars (undated, 1950-1960) contains information regarding programs held by specific companies or other organizations for their employees. The series is arranged alphabetically by the town in which the seminars were held.
Series IX: Mutual Security Agency (undated, 1952-1953) documents programs sponsored by M.S.A. and administered by the LEC. The bulk of the series relates to the trade union program held in 1953. Included in the files are correspondence, photographs, reports, and other printed materials.
Series X: Workshops (undated, 1950-1956) contains information regarding workshops sponsored by LEC and is arranged by subject.
Series XI: Connecticut Valley Hospital (circa 1960s) [RESTRICTED] is composed of records of unionized employees at the Hospital. Documentation of employee grievances is included. Grievances files are restricted; see University Archivist concerning access.
Series XII: Reports (1950-1965) contains studies created by and for LEC for adminstrative, training, promotional, and research purposes. Also included are newsclippings on labor-related articles. The series is arranged alphabetically by publication name, author, or subject.
Acquisition Information
The records of the Labor Education Center were transferred to the Historical Manuscripts and Archives division (now Archives & Special Collections) of the University of Connecticut Library in August 1981 by George E. O'Connell, Director of the Labor Education Center.
Access
The collection is open and available for research with the exception of Series I: Personnel Files, and Series XI: Connecticut Valley Hospital.
Hospitals; Labor unions; Legal aid; Philippines (nation); Industrial relations; Congresses and conventions; Grievance procedures; Education; Universities and colleges; Medical jurisprudence; Connecticut (state); Head Start programs; Arbitration, Industrial; Community development; Job security; Shop stewards; Actions and defenses; Windham (inhabited place); Storrs (inhabited place); Publications (documents); Correspondence; Press releases; Administrative records; Photographs; Financial Records; Fliers (printed matter); Employees--Rating of; Labor movement; Medical care; Middletown (inhabited place); Labor; University extension; University of Connecticut. Labor Education Center; University of Connecticut
- Series I: Administrative correspondence files, 1954-1966
- Series II: John Glynn Files, undated, 1949-1968
  - General
    - Correspondence, (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - Funds and foundations
    - Invitations to other institutions' programs
    - Labor and legislation
    - Miscellaneous
    - Newsletters
    - Other labor education programs
    - Photographs
    - Registration expenses
    - Staff relations
    - University Labor Educational Association members
  - Labor Education Center: Courses and Workshops
    - Correspondence
    - "Job Evaluation"
    - "Labor looks at Connecticut"
    - Lists of union members attending LEC courses
    - Potential teachers for educational programs
    - Workshops
  - Labor Management Institute
    - "Grievance Procedures"
    - Programs offered by LMI
  - Publications
    - Articles re: labor education at UConn
    - "Connecticut Buzzer"
  - The Freeworker
    - Labor books—advertisements
    - Newsletters and bulletins, (3 folders)
  - University of Philippines
    - Budgets
    - Contracts, (2 folders)
    - Contracts proposed
    - Exhibits (extra copies)
    - Insurance
    - LEC Newsletter
    - Miscellaneous
    - Misconduct complaints and negotiations
    - Newsclippings, 1954-1962
    - Photographs
    - Philippines—Brazilian study group
    - Philippine programs and union information, (2 folders)
    - Philipines trade union council minutes, 1954
    - Philippine trade union group
    - Philippine visitors, 1957-1960; (2 folders)
    - Progress reports
    - Suspension reports
    - Vidal Tan: University of Philippines complaints
    - University senate minutes, 1962
- Series III: Unions and Organizations, undated
  - AFL-CIO (Box 4)
  - AFSCME
  - American Association of University Professors
  - American Federation of Teachers
  - American Nurses Association
  - American Thread Institute
  - Communication Workers of America, (2 folders)
  - Connecticut State Federation of Teachers
  - Council 16, State Employees (Box 5)
    - Contracts and Agreements
  - Federation of University Teachers
  - F.O.A.
  - International Association of Machinists
  - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions
  - International Cooperation Administration
  - International Ladies Garment Workers Union
  - Iron Workers
  - Machinists constituents
  - Mansfield Democrats
  - Oil Chemical Atomic Workers, (2 folders)
  - Railroad unions—Canada
  - Taft-Hartley discussion group
  - Teachers union
  - Textile Workers Union of America publications
  - United Auto Workers
  - United Steelworkers of America
  - Wilbur Cross Democratic Club
  - Young Unionist Action League
- Series IV: Windham Area Community Action Program [WACAP], 1965-1970
  - Accounts and expenses (Box 6)
  - Amended by-laws
  - Bartow, Marlain M.
  - Board of Directors, 1967-1970
  - Board meeting files, 1968-1969
  - Board minutes, 1968-1970
  - CAP management guide
  - Central administration
  - Certificates of appreciation
  - Community Action Agency
  - Community organization
  - Consumer action
  - Continuous Enrichment Program
  - Department of Community Affairs
  - Fair Living Standards Act
  - Food Service
  - Gibson, Marshall (executive director)
  - Glynn, John (V.P., board of directors)
  - Glynn, John: personnel policies
  - Headstart—full year
  - Headstart—summer
  - Job Development Program
  - Legal services (Tolland-Windham)
  - Manpower
  - Mansfield Community Action Group
  - Miscellaneous
  - Monthly state of the agency, 1970
  - NECCA conference
  - Neighborhood services
  - Newsclipping
  - Pamphlets and bulletins
  - Personnel policies, 1965-1970; (4 folders)
  - Petition of support
  - Planning and development program
  - Planning grant expansion
  - Policy and administration
  - Problems in Windham County
  - Programs
  - Program accounts
  - Program annual reports, 1967-1970
  - Program: board approved, 1970
  - Program: board opposed, 1970
  - Putnam gas station project
  - Report of budgets
  - Ivera, Minnie
  - Senior Citizen center
  - Staff memos
  - Statement of purpose
  - State of Connecticut, Dept. of Community Affairs
  - Statistics survey, 1967
  - Structure and operation manual
  - Summer neighborhood youth corps
  - WACAP annual report
  - WACAP, 1970
  - Willimantic
    - Early education program
    - Mansfield full year recreation program
    - Mansfield summer recreation program
- Series V: Extension Programs, undated, 1948-1968
  - Ansonia (Box 7)
    - Lecture series, 1955
    - Conferences, 1966
  - Bethel, conferences, 1967
  - Bloomfield, J.M. Ney Co., Mgmt Group, 1960
  - Bridgeport
    - Conferences, 1965-1968; (2 folders)
    - Extension programs
  - Bristol
    - Conferences, 1966-1967; (2 folders)
    - Public programs, 1954
  - Danbury, conferences, 1966-1968; (2 folders)
  - Danielson
    - F.W. Sickles Co., human relations, 1952
    - F.W. Sickles Co., supervisory training, 1954
    - Conferences, 1966-1968; (2 folders)
    - Lecture series, 1950
    - Extension programs, 1951
    - "Current issues in Labor Mgmt"
  - East Hartford, conferences, 1967
  - Fairfield, conferences, 1968
  - Groton, conferences, 1968
  - Hamden, conferences, 1966-1967
  - Hartford
    - Conferences, 1963-1969; (2 folders)
    - Adult school, 1949-1950
    - Collective bargaining, 1949
    - Extension programs, 1949
    - Lecture series, 1949
  - Manchester, conferences, 1953, 1966
  - Meriden, labor-management, 1956 (Box 8)
  - Middletown
    - Conferences, 1963-1965
    - Public extension programs, 1954
  - Milford
    - Conferences, 1963-1965
    - Public extension programs, 1954
  - Moosup, Majestic Metals supervisory training course, 1951
  - New Britain
    - Conferences, 1965-1968; (2 folders)
    - Public programs, 1953
  - New Haven
    - Conferences, 1963-1969; (2 folders)
    - Plasticrete Corp. supervisory training, 1958
  - New London, conferences, 1964-1967; (2 folders)
  - North Haven (Box 9)
    - Conferences, 1967; (2 folders)
    - Dynamics of union leadership
    - Union aircraft, 1956
  - Norwalk, Norwich conference, 1964-1968; (2 folders)
  - Norwich
    - State hospital employees, steward training, 1958
    - State hospital employees, 1963
  - Oakville, Scovill Mfg. Co. supervisory training, 1955
  - Plainfield
    - Royal Metals—United Steelworkers, local 3501, 1959
    - Steelworkers, 1956
    - United Steelworkers of America, local 3501, 1959
  - Plainville, castings—United Steelworkers, local 3501, 1959
  - Rogers, Rogers Corp. and IBPM-AFL, 1952
  - Seymour
    - Mfg. Co. UAW, 1963
    - UAW-CIO, 1952
  - Southbury, Local 321, council 16, AFL-CIO, 1958
  - Southbury/Southington, conference, 1967; (2 folders)
  - Southington
    - Conference, 1954
    - IAM Lodge 1746A, 1960, 1963; (3 folders)
  - Stamford
    - Adult School, 1948-1950; (6 folders)
    - Conferences, 1963-1968; (2 folders)
    - Current labor law, 1949
    - Extension program
    - "History and Organization of American Labor Unions"
    - Human relations in industry, 1948-1949
    - IAM grievance procedure and labor, 1954
    - IAM steward training course, 1954
    - Introduction to industrial and labor relations
    - Public extension program
    - Steward training
  - Stonington, American Velvet Co. supervisory training, 1957
  - Storrs
    - Conference, 1963-1968; (2 folders)
    - Connecticut vocational technical school directors conference, 1953
    - Human relations training boom or bust LMI and ASTD
    - IAM advances leadership school, 1960
  - Stratford
    - Conferences, 1965-1967
    - IJWU local 210, 1954
  - Thomas, UAW local 1082, 1953
  - Thomaston, UAW local, 1961
  - Thompsonville
    - TWUA local 2188, 1957
    - TWUA Bigelow Stamford Carpet Co., 1956
  - Torrington
    - Conferences, 1965-1968; (2 folders)
    - UAW-CIO local 507, 1953
    - UAW local 507-512, 1953
    - Union hardware, local 247, 1952
    - Metal products, 1953
  - Wallingford
    - American Cyanimid Co., 1952-1953; (2 folders)
    - Jewelry workers local 45, 1950
    - Advanced Conferences series YMCA Mgmt. Development Group, 1954
  - Waterbury
    - Conferences, 1964-1966; (2 folders)
    - Waterbury Companies, Inc., contracts and admin. course, 1952
    - Adult School, 1949-1950; (2 folders)
    - Watchworkers Local 24369, 1951
    - Brassworkers Union Local 1251, 1951
    - UAW, 1953
    - Wheeler Insulated Wire Co. local 1661, 1953
    - American Brass UAW local 1078, 1956
    - United Steelworkers of America, 1957
    - Weekend Institute UAW, 1957-1960; (4 folders)
    - American Brass Local 1028, 1962
    - Scovill UAW local 1604, 1951, 1963; (4 folders)
    - United Steelworkers, 1957
  - Watertown
    - Public programs supervisory training, 1955
    - Human relations in industry, 1955
  - West Hartford, conferences, 1966-1968; (2 folders)
  - West Haven, United Rubberworkers of America, 1956
  - Willimantic
    - Conferences, 1964-1967; (2 folders)
    - William Brand and Co., 1951-1953; (2 folders)
    - Extension Programs, 1950
    - Textile Workers of America, 1958
    - TWUA Local 460, 1957
  - Windor Locks, Hartford Aircraft Lodge 743 IAM, 1956-1957
  - Winsted, Hudson Wire Co., Local 1603 UAW, 1954
- Series VI: LEC-Sponsored Conferences, undated, 1947-1969
  - Arbitration in labor-management relations, 1954, 1956; (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Cole humanities seminar at Pennsylvania State
  - Connecticut attorney's conference, 1956
  - Danbury education conference, 1964
  - El Salvadoran labor officials, AID, 1962
  - Employment security conference, 1954
  - (John) Glynn conference, 1963-1966; (2 folders)
  - Guaranteed Annual Wage conference, 1956
  - Highway department, AFSCME, 1962
  - International printing pressmen, eastern conference, 1966-1969
  - Interstate Conference on labor statistics, 1967
  - Korea's impact on industrial Connecticut, 1950
  - Labor advisory committee, 1962
  - Labor education conference, (2 folders)
  - Labor conference, Bureau of training and apprenticeship, 1958
  - Labor Management Institute, 1954, 1958; (3 folders)
  - Labor and the community, 1963-1964
  - LMI conferences, 1947-1955; (8 folders)
  - Labor relations center meeting, 1951
  - Machinists' conference, 1953-1961; (11 folders)
  - Management conference, 1953
  - Meatcutters, stewards, AFL Institute, 1950
  - Michigan State international affairs conference, 1962
  - New dimenstions in labor management relations, 1957
  - New horizons in labor education, 1962; (5 folders)
  - Papermakers and paperworkers conference, AFL-CIO, 1957
  - Rehabilitation and labor, 1964; (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Seminar, labor department, 1960
  - Social work institute, 1959-1961
  - State, municipal employees conference, 1957
  - State, county, and municipal employees-AFL, 1953, 1957, 1960; (3 folders)
  - Steelworkers institute, 1953-1958; (7 folders)
  - Teachers, American Federation of, 1960-1962; (2 folders)
  - Teachers, Connecticut Federation of, 1960 (Box 12)
  - Telephone Workers, Connecticut Union of, 1960-1963
  - TWUA, 1950-1956; (6 folders)
  - Time study workshop, 1963
  - Trainmen, annual conference, 1958-1959; (2 folders)
- Series VII: Labor Training Programs, undated, 1949-1969
  - Ansonia (Box 13)
    - Ansonia Wire and Cable Co., IBEW, 1953
  - Bridgeport
    - Amalgamated locals 505 and 877, 1951
    - Avoc. local 1010, 1953-54, 1960; (3 folders)
    - Industrial union council, 1957
    - Dictaphone employees union, 1956
    - Labor education program, 1960
    - Lycoming division, 1954
    - Sikorsky, 1951-1960; (4 folders)
    - Steward training, local 877, 1951
    - Underwood Corp. local 267, 1956-1957; (4 folders)
    - United Steelworkers of America, 1955; (2 folders)
    - URCLPWA local 176 and 283, 1952
  - Bristol
    - Ingraham Co., IUE local 260, 1950
    - Union rights and representatives, 1960
  - Danielson
    - TWUA local 638 and 1196, 1951
  - East Hartford
    - Union Leadership training, 1957
    - IAM-AFL district lodge 91, 1953
    - IAM, 1957
  - Georgetown
    - Gilbert and Bennett Wire Co., 1956-1957; (4 folders)
  - Hamden
    - United dairy workers, 1960
    - Steel metal workers, 1961
  - Hartford
    - AFSCME, 1949, 1954; (2 folders)
    - , AFL joint locals, 1951
    - AFL-CIO labor education program, 1959
    - Aircraft lodge, 1953
    - Apprentice training course, 1957
    - Democracy in America, 1962
    - Emhart Manufacturing Co., 1957; (4 folders)
    - Fall program, 1960-1963
    - Fuller Brush Co., 1955, 1957; (4 folders)
    - IAI, 1958
    - IAM, 1956
    - IBEW Union Rights, 1959
    - Labor council, 1958
    - Labor department seminar, 1956
    - Labor relations school, 1960
    - Niles-Bement Pond, 1955
    - Officers training program, 1952
    - Pipefitting Co., atomic energy, 1956
    - Royal Typewriter Co., 1955
    - Sheetmetal workers, 1961
    - Spring programs, 1961; (2 folders)
    - Stewards' Club meeting, 1953
    - Textile workers, 1959
    - UAW, 1952, 1958-59; (3 folders)
    - Underwood stewards course, 1963
    - Weekend Institute (UAW), 1956
    - "What makes a city", 1963
  - Ivoryton
    - International Union of Upholsterers, 1951
  - Manchester
    - Connecticut Union and Telephone Workers, 1960
  - Meriden
    - ALW, 1962
    - Allied Industrial Workers of America, 1959-1960; (3 folders)
    - IUE-CIO Local 285, 1951
    - UAW allied industrial workers, 1958
  - Middletown
    - Connecticut State Hospital employees, 1956, 58; (2 folders)
    - Russell Manufacturing Co., 1950
    - UAW time study, 1963
  - Naugatuck
    - United Rubber Workers of America, 1950-56, 1962; (6 folders)
  - New Britain (Box 14)
    - Grand Manufacturing Co., 1953
    - Fafnir Bearing Co., 1956-58; (2 folders)
    - IAM lodge, 1961-62; (3 folders)
    - Local AIU, 1963
  - New Haven
    - AFL, 1951
    - Connecticut State Labor Council convention, 1969
    - Federation of utility employees, 1962
    - IAM, 1958; (3 folders)
    - Industrial union school locals, 1951
    - Joint council, 1951
    - Municipal employees, 1956-57
    - Telephone workers, 1957
    - Victory lodge IAM, 1961
  - Newtown
    - AFL-CIO local 203, 1957
  - Storrs
    - Electrical Workers International local 1013, 1961
    - Executive group training, 1950-1951; (2 folders)
    - Foreman training course, 1950-1951; (2 folders)
    - Machinists basic leadership school, 1960-1962; (3 folders)
    - Management training conference, 1956
    - Retail clerks summer school, 1961 (Box 15)
    - Steelworkers summer school, 1959-1962; (5 folders)
    - Steward training, 1950, 1963-67; (2 folders)
    - Supervisory training school, 1950-1952; (4 folders)
    - Teachers (American Federation) summer school, 1959-1961; (3 folders)
    - Textile workers union summer school, 1952-53,19 57; (3 folders)
- Series VIII: Corporate Sponsored Seminars, undated, 1950-1960
  - Berlin, municipal employee relations (CL&P), 1959 (Box 16)
  - Bridgeport, unity mason conference, 1958
  - East Killingly, Acme Cotton Products Co., 1951, 1956; (2 folders)
  - Hartford
    - Allen Manufacturing Co., 1955
    - Anemostat Corporation of America, 1952
    - Hartford National Bank and Trust Co., 1958
    - Jacobs Manufacturing Co., 1955
    - Pratt and Whitney, 1956-1957; (2 folders)
  - New Haven, American Machine Co., 1955
  - New London, Social Implications of Labor Relations, 1954
  - Oakville, Scovill Manufacturing Co., 1956
  - Rogers, Rogers Corporation lectur series, 1952
  - Seymour, Waterman Pen Co., 1954, 1955; (2 folders)
  - Stamford
    - Pitney Bowes Inc., 1950
    - Unit Masonry conference, 1958
  - Stratford, Manning, Maxwell & Moore, Inc., 1954, 1958; (2 folders)
  - Terryville, Eagle Lock Co., 1955
  - Torrington
    - Industrial Management Club, 1957
    - Torrington Manufacturing Co., 1952
  - Waterbury
    - American Brass Co., 1955
    - Waterbury Manufacturing Co., 1951-1952; (3 folders)
  - Williamantic, Willimantic Industrial Forum, 1957-5198
- Series IX: Mutual Security Agency, undated, 1952-1953
  - Trade Union Program, 1953; (9 folders) (Box 17)
  - Management Program, 1952
  - Time and motion study, 1953
  - Work-study training program, (2 folders)
- Series X: Workshops, undated, 1950-1956
  - General, 1950-1956; (5 folders) (Box 18)
  - Labor Management, 1954-1955; (2 folders)
- Series XI: Connecticut Valley Hospital [RESTRICTED]
- Series XII: Reports, undated, 1950-1965
  - Babbidge, Homer D., "Leading to the Highest" (Box 20)
  - Basic and applied research proposal, 1965
  - Business and labor comm. "The Peoples' Right", 1967
  - Chief employment compensation benefits
  - CT CIO council voter registration survey, 1954
  - "Connecticut Labor Situation", 1962-1963
  - Current labor problems
  - Democratic party
  - Democracy in trade unions
  - Danish time study team, 1954
  - Federal tax adjustment act, 1966